The world is changed.
世界发生了变化
! feel it in the water.
我在水中能感觉到
! feel it in the earth.
我在地上能看到
! smell it in the air.
我在空中能璃到
Much that once was...
原有的一切
. AS lost
所剩无几
For none now live who remember it.
过去的记忆荡然无存
It began with the forging of the Great Rings.
这个故事从打造19术魔戒开始
Three were given fo the Elves.
3枚送给了精灵王
Immortal, wisest and fairest of all beings.
他们是世界上 最聪明其良和长寿的一族
Seven to the Dwarf-lords:
7枚送给了矮人贵族
Great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
他们是最伟大的山酒开掘者和工匠
And nine...
另外9枚
..nine rings were gifted to the race of Men...
那9枚送给了人类
... who, above all else, desire power.
他们是最最渴望力量的生命
For within these rings was bound the strength and will fo govern each race.
这9枚魔式只有一定权限 从而使各方彼此制约
But they were ail of them deceived.
可是大家都被莹在鼓里
For another ring was made.
因为还有一枚魔戒
!n the land of Mordor, in the fires of Mount Doom...
在魔多的土地上 在来日山的烈焰中
...the Dark Lord Sauron forged in secret a Master Ring...
黑暗魔君索伦打造了 能够掌控一切的
...f0 control all others.
至尊魔戒
And into this Ring he poured his cruelty, his malice...
他在这枚魔戒中注入了自己的残暴那恶
..and his will fo dominate all life.
以及主宰众生的意志
One Ring fo rule them all.
这枚至高无上的魔戒之王
One by one...
渐渐地
...the Free Lands of Middle-earth fell fo the power of the Ring.
把中土的自由土地 一片片地纳入了自己的光环
But there were some who resisted.
但是抵抗的力量并没有消失
A Last Alliance of Men and Elves marched against the armies of Mordor.
人类和精灵组成了最后的联盟 向魔多的军队宣战
And on the slopes of Mount Doom, they fought for the freedom of Middle-earth.
他们在末日山上 为中土的自由浴血奋战
Victory was near.
胜利就在眼前
But the power of the Ring...
但是至尊魔戒的力量
... could not be undone.
无法消灭
It was in this moment...
在这即将绝望的最后关头
...that Isifdur, son of the king, took up his father's sword.
人类国王的儿子埃西铎 接过了父亲手中的宝剑
Sauron, the enemy of the Free Peoples of Middle-earth, was defeated.
索伦 中土自由人民的死敌 终于被打败了
The Ring passed fo Isildur...
埃西铎得到了至尊魔戒
... who had this one chance to destroy evil forever.
他可以借此机会永远铲除那恶
But the hearts of Men...
但是人类的心
..are easily corrupted.
最容易被患惑
And the Ring of Power has a will of ifs own.
至苯魔戒并不肯善罢甘休
It betrayed Isildur fo his death.
它引诱埃西铎走向死亡
And some things that should not have been forgotten...
本来不应该筷却的事情
... were lost.
就去却了
History became legend...
历史变成了传说
.. legend became myth.
传说变成了神话
And for two and a half thousand years...
2二5自年过去了
...the Ring passed out of all knowledge.
至尊魔戒再也不被人提起
Until, when chance came...
直到有一天
.. if ensnared a new bearer.
它又找到了新的持有者
My precious.
我的宝贝
The Ring came fo the creature Gollum...
小怪物咕噜得到了至尊魔戒
... who took it deep into the tunnels of the Misty Mountains.
他把它带进了迷宫山的隧道深处
And there it consumed him.
爱不释手地把玩着
It came to me.
它归我了
My own. My love. My own.
归我了 亲爱的 归我了
My precious.
我的宝贝
The Ring brought fo Gollum unnatural long life.
至苯魔戒使咕噜长生不老
For 500 years it poisoned his mind.
5上自年的时间里它在阴暗的洞穴中
And in the gloom of Gollum's cave, it waited.
茶毒着他的心灵 也在宕伺着时机
Darkness crept back into the forests of the world.
那恶悄悄潜回了世界森林
Rumor grew of a shadow in the East...
从政恶的远方传来谣言
... whispers of a nameless fear.
散布着无名的恐悍
And the Ring of Power perceived...
至尊魔戒感到
... Its time had now come.
时机已经成熟了
It abandoned Gollum.
于是它抛弃了咕噜
But something happened then the Ring did not intend.
但接下来的事情却出人意料
It was picked up by the most unlikely creature imaginable.
它被一种最不应该得到它的生物得到了
What's this?
这是什么
A Hobbit.
一个需比特族人
Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
夏尔国的比尔博' 巴金斯
A ring.
一枚戒指
Lost!
不见了
My precious is lost!
我的宝贝不见了
For the time will soon come...
迎接考验的时刻到了
... when Hobbits will shape the fortunes of all.
中土人的命运 掌握在了需比特人手中
The road goes ever on and on
虽然路程尚遥远
Down from the door where it began
我朝着那里走不停
Now far ahead the road has gone
漫漫长路望不到边
A wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins.
巫师永远不会来晚 佛罗多“' 巴金斯
Nor is he early. He arrives precisely when he means to.
也不会来早 他总是来得不晚不早
It's wonderful to see you, Gandalf!
见到你真高兴 鞭道夫
You didn't think I'd miss your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
我误不了你叔叔比尔博的生日宴会
What news of the outside world? Tell me everything.
外界有什么消息? 告诉我所有的一切
Everything? You're far too eager and curious for a Hobbit.
所有的一切? 这可不像与世无争的蝴比特人
Most unnatural.
口气太大了
Well, what can I tell you?
好吧 我能告诉你什么呢?
Life in the wide world goes on much as it has this past Age.
从上个世纪起这世界没有太大的变化
Full of its own comings and goings.
斗转星移 一如既往
Scarcely aware of the existence of Hobbits.
很少有人注意到埠比特人的存在
For which I am very thankful.
真是谢天谢地
It's Gandalfl
是甘道夫
The long-expected party.
期队已久的宴会
How is the old rascal?
这老家伙 他在搞什么
I hear it's going to be a party of special magnificence.
我听说这将是一次盛况空前的宴会
You know Bilbo. He's got the whole place in an uproar.
他说整个国家都在谈论这次刘会
Well, that should please him.
那会让他感到很开心
-Half the Shire's been invited. -Gracious me.
一夏尔国有一半人受到邀请 -我的上帝
-He's up to something. -Oh, really?
他在筹划什么事情 那好吧 你可别说破
Before you came along, we Bagginses were very well thought of.
你来之前巴金斯家的人考虑事情很周到
Never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
从来不去冒险或做什么出格的事情
If you're referring to the incident with the dragon, I was barely involved.
如果你是指遭遇巨龙的事 那和我可没太大的关系
All l did was give your uncle a little nudge out of the door.
我所做的只是鼓励他到外面去走走
Whatever you did, you've been officially labeled a disturber of the peace.
不管你做了什么 大家都认为 是你搅乱了我们的平静生活
Oh, really?
是吗
Gandalf! Gandalfl
甘道夫 甘道夫
Fireworks, Gandalfl
烟火 甘道夫
-Gandalfl -Fireworks, Gandalfl
一鞭道夫 一放烟火 甘道夫
Gandalf?
甘道夫
-I'm glad you're back. -So am I, dear boy.
一我真高兴你回来 一我也是 好孩子
Soaml.
我也是
No, thank you!
不 谢谢
We don't want any more visitors, well-wishers or distant relations!
我们不接待来访者 祝寿者以及各种亲威
And what about very old friends?
连老朋友也不欢迎吗
Gandalf?
甘道夫
-Bilbo Baggins. -My dear Gandalfl
一比尔博' 巴金斯 一亲爱的鞭道夫
Good to see you. 111 years old! Who would believe it?
苑到你真高兴 111岁 谁能相信?
You haven't aged a day.
你还是那么年轻
Come on, come in!
来 快请进 快请进
Welcome, welcome.
欢迎 欢迎
Oh, here we are.
来吧
Tea? Or maybe something a little stronger?
喝茶吗 要不来点刺激的?
I've got a few bottles of the Old Winyard left. 1296.
我有几瓶1296年的葡萄酒
Very good year. Almost as old as ! am.
是陈年老窜 它与我的年龄差不多大
It was laid down by my father. What say we open one, eh?
是我父亲留下的 开一瓶怎么样?
Just tea, thank you.
还是喝茶吧 谢谢
l was expecting you sometime last week.
我以为你上礼拜就到
Not that it matters. You come and go as you please. Always have and always will.
你一向我行我素 来去无踪
You caught me a bit unprepared. We've only got cold chicken and a bit of pickle....
所以我有点措手不及了 只是有凉的鸡肉和泡菜
There's some cheese here. No, that won't do.
这儿还有点奶酪 不 这怎么行
We've got raspberry jam, an apple tart...
这儿还有草莓次和苹果馅饼
But not much for afters. Oh, no, we're all right.
当饭后甜点少了点 不 问题解决了
I've just found some sponge cake.
我又找到几块蛋糕
I could make you some eggs if you'd--
我可以炒几个鸡蛋
-Just tea, thank you. -Oh, right.
一我只喝茶 谢谢 -那好吧
-You don't mind if ! eat, do you? -No, not at all.
一我吃你不介意吧? -不不介意
Bilbo! Bilbo Baggins!
比尔博' 巴金斯
I'm not at home!
我不在家
l've got to get away from these confounded relatives, hanging on the bell all day...
我必须躲开这些没完没了的亲威
...never giving me a moment's peace.
他们一时一刻也不让我安宁
I want to see mountains again. Mountains, Gandalfl
我打算再去游览名山 我喜欢山 甘道夫
And then find somewhere quiet where I can finish my book. Oh, tea.
然后我就找个安静的地方 把我的书写完哦 茶
-So you mean to go through with your plan? -Yes, yes. It's all in hand.
-你的意思是说你要完成你的计划 -是的 一切都准备好了
All the arrangements are made.
可以说万事俱备
Oh, thank you.
谢谢
Frodo suspects something.
佛罗多已经察觉有事
Of course he does. He's a Baggins...
当然会察觉 他是巴金斯家的人
...not some blockheaded Bracegirdle from Hardbottle.
和布茉斯高家那些 答头答脑的人就是不一样
You will tell him, won't you?
你会把事情告诉他 对吗
-Yes, yes. -He's very fond of you.
-是的 是的 -他韭常爱你
I know.
我知道
He'd probably come with me if l asked him.
如果我提出要求他会和我一起走
I think in his heart, Frodo's still in love with the Shire.
不过我想佛罗多韭常热爱夏尔国
The woods, the fields.
草原 田野
Little rivers.
小溪
lam old, Gandalf.
我老了 甘道夫
I know I don't look it, but I'm beginning to feel it in my heart.
我知道自己不太显老 可是我从心里已经开始感觉到了
feel thin.
我 我有点力不从心了
Sort of stretched...
我过于勉强自己了
.. like butter scraped over too much bread.
就像一块黄油要抹太多的面包
I need a holiday. A very long holiday.
我需要一个假期 很长的假期
And don't expect I shall return.
估计我不会回来了
In fact, ! mean not to.
实际上我不想回来了
Old Toby. The finest weed in the Southfarthing.
这是老托比种的 小丘南面最好的烟草
Gandalf, my old friend...
甘道夫 我的老朋友
... this will be a night to remember.
这是一个值得纪念的夜晚
Hello, hello.
你好
Fatty Bolger. Lovely to see you. Welcome, welcome.
博尔格 很高兴苑到你 欢迎
Go on, Sam. Ask Rosie for a dance.
快去吧 山姆 快去邀罗丝跳舞
-[ think I'll just have another ale. -Oh, no, you don't.
-我想再喝杯玫芽酒 -不 那可不行
Go on!
你快去
So there I was...
就在这个时候
..at the mercy of three monstrous trolls.
我落在了三个大怪物的手里
And they were all arguing amongst themselves...
它们为怎样吃我们争论不休
.. about how they were going to cook us.
是放在火上烤着吃呢
Whether it be turned on a spit, or to sit on us one by one, squash us into jelly.
还是把我们一个个都生知活剥了
They spent so much time arguing the whithertos and the whyfors...
他们没完没了地争论着 种种原因和理由
.. that the sun's first light crept over the top of the trees...
一直到早晨太阳有朴上了树梢
..and turned them all to stone!
它们全都变成了石头
Quickly.
快点
Up they go!
开花了
No, the big one.
不不 拿那个大的 大的
-Done! -You're supposed to stick it in the ground.
-好了 一你扶着它
-It is in the ground. -Outside!
一不应该你扶着 一应该你扶着 是你的主意
Watch out for the dragon!
比尔博 有巨龙
Nonsense. There hasn't been a dragon in these parts for a thousand years.
巨龙 哪儿来的什么巨龙 那都是多少年以前的事了
-That was good. -Let's get another one.
一太好了 - 再去弄一个
Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took.
梅里亚， 巴克 皮平，图克
I might've Known.
你们这两个的蛋扳
Speech, Bilbo!
比尔博 请讲话
Speech!
请讲话
My dear Bagginses and Boffins...
亲爱的巴金斯家和波芬家的亲人
... looks and Brandybucks...
还有图克家和布兰巴克家的
..Grubbs, Chubbs...
葛卢伯家 丘伯家
... Hornblowers...
夫恩布洛尔家的
...Bolgers...
博尔格家的
...Bracegirdles...
莱斯克特家
-...and Proudfoots. -Proudfeet!
-和布劳福特家 -是布劳菲特
Today is my 111th birthday!
今天是我111岁的生日
Happy birthday!
生日快乐
But alas, eleventy-one years is far too short a time to live among...
可是生活在如此优秀和 善良的需比特家族中间
.. such excellent and admirable Hobbits.
这111年又是何等的短暂
I don't know half of you half as well as I should like...
我对你们的了解还不及我想要的一半
..and I like less than half of you half as well as you deserve.
我对你们的热爱 还不及你们应该得到的一半
I have things to do.
可是 我还有其它的事情
I've put this off far too long.
我尽量拖延分别的时间
I regret to announce this is the end!
我遗憾地宣布我要走了
I'm going now.
我这就走
I bid you all a very fond farewell.
祝你们大家万事如意
Goodbye.
再见
I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
我想你一定认为那样做很聪明
Come on, Gandalf. Did you see their faces?
得了 甘道夫 难道你没看见 大家脸上的表情吗
There are many magic rings in this world, and none of them should be used lightly.
这个世界上有很多魔戒 但我们不应该轻易使用它们
It was just a bit of fun.
我只是觉得很有趣
Oh, you're probably right, as usual.
也许你说得对 你一贯正确
-You will keep an eye on Frodo, won't you? -Two eyes.
一你会照顾佛罗多 对吗? 一何止是照顾
As often as I can spare them.
我会无微不至地关心他
-I'm leaving everything to him. -What about this ring of yours?
=-我会把一切都留给他 一包括那枚戒指 对吗
-ls that staying too? -Yes, yes.
-你会把它留下吗 -是的 是的
It's in an envelope over there on the mantelpiece.
它就在攻炉上的那个信封里
No. Wait, it's...
不 等等
... here in my pocket.
它在我的口袋里
Isn't that--? Isn't that odd, now?
很奇怪 不是吗
Yet, after all, why not?
为什么不呢?
-Why shouldn't I keep it? -[ think you should leave the ring behind.
一为什么不能带走它? 一我认为你应该把它留下
Is that so hard?
很为难 是吗
Well, no.
不不
And yes.
是的
Now it comes to it, I don't feel like parting with it.
现在要分手了 我真有点舍不得
It's mine. I found it! It came to me!
你知道我得到它有多人么不容易
-There's no need to get angry. -Well, if I'm angry, it's your fault!
一为什么如此激动 一我当然激动 全都是你的错
It's mine.
它是我的
My own.
我的
-My precious. -Precious?
一我的宝贝 一宝贝?
It's been called that before, but not by you.
那是它从前的名字不过你并不知道
What business is it of yours what I do with my own things?
不 它和你有什么关系 我在处置自己的东西
I think you've had that ring quite long enough.
我想它在你手里已经太久了
-You want it for yourself! -Bilbo Baggins!
-你打算据为已有吗 一比尔博' 巴金斯
Do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks.
不要以为我在和你要心眼
lam not trying to rob you.
我不想抢你的东西
I'm trying to help you.
我只想帮助你
All your long years, we've been friends.
在你漫长的一生我们一直是朋友
Trust me as you once did.
要像从前那样相信我
Let it go.
放弃它吧
You're right, Gandalf.
你是对的 鞭道夫
The ring must go to Frodo.
我一定把它交给佛罗多
It's late. The road is long.
时间不早了 长路漫漫
Yes, it is time.
是的 我该动身了
The ring is still in your pocket.
戒指还在你口袋
I've thought up an ending for my book:
我的书打算这样结尾
"And he lived happily ever after to the end of his days."
从此以后他过着地福的生活 直到离开人世
And I'm sure you will, my dear friend.
你的愿望会实现 朋友
Goodbye, Gandalf.
再见 甘道夫
Goodbye, dear Bilbo.
再见了 亲爱的比尔博
The road goes ever on and on
漫漫长路望不到边
Until our next meeting.
我们还会再见面的
It's mine. My own.
它是我的 我的
My precious.
我的宝贝
Riddles in the dark.
幕后交易
Bilbo!
比尔博 比尔博
My precious.
宝贝
He's gone, hasn't he?
他走了 是吗
He talked for so long about leaving...
他已经说了很长时间
...[ didn't think he'd really do it.
我没想到他真的会走
Gandalf?
甘道夫
Bilbo's ring.
这是他的戒指
He's gone to stay with the Elves.
他到精灵那儿去了
He's left you Bag End.
他把酒留给你了
Along with all his possessions.
还有他的全部家产
The ring is yours now.
这枚戒指归你了
-Put it somewhere out of sight. -Where are you going?
一放在没人知道的地方 一你要去哪儿?
-There are some things that I must see to. -What things?
-我要去做一件事情 -什么事情?
-Questions. Questions that need answering. -You've only just arrived.
-寻找答案 必须寻找的答案 一可你刚刚才来
I don't understand.
我不明白
Neither do I.
我也不明白
Keep it secret.
不要告诉任何人
Keep it safe.
收好
Shire!
夏尔国
Baggins!
巴金斯
"The year 3434 of the Second Age.
第二纪3434年
Here follows the account of Isildur, High King of Gondor...
下面是人类大王埃西铎
..and the finding of the Ring of Power."
有关发现至尊魔式的记载
"It has come fo me.
它属于我了
The One Ring. It shall be an heirloom of my kingdom.
这枚至尊魔戒 它将成为我国的传世之宝
All those who follow in my bloodline Shall be bound to ifs fate...
我的子子孙孙王秋万代 都将受到它的庇护
.. for I will risk no hurt fo the Ring.
我不会让它受到丝毫损坏
It is precious fo me...
它是我的宝贝
.. though I buy it with great pain.
我为它付出了太多
The markings upon the band begin to fade.
它上面的印记开始消退
The writing, which at first was as clear as red flame, has all but disappeared.
原来清晰无比的文字
A secret now that only fire can tell."
只有烈焰才能辉映出它的秘密
Shire.
夏尔国
Baggins.
巴金斯
There's no Bagginses around here. They're all up in Hobbiton.
这一带没有姓巴金斯的 他们都住在需比特
That way.
在那边
-Good night.
一晚安
Good night, Sam.
一晚安 山姆 一晚安 佛罗多
Is it secret? Is it safe?
没告诉别人吧 魔戒还在吗
What are you doing?
你干什么
Hold out your hand, Frodo.
伸出手来 佛罗多
It's quite cool.
它是凉的
What can you see?
能看到什么
Can you see anything?
你看到了什么
Nothing.
没什么
There's nothing.
什么也没有
Wait.
等等
There are markings.
上夯有印记
It's some form of Elvish. I can't read it.
好像是精灵的文字 我看不懂
There are few who can.
很少有人能看懂
The language is that of Mordor, which will not utter here.
这是魔多语 我现在不便讲
In the common tongue, it says:
它的大意是说
"One Ring to rule them all...
至苯魔戒 统治一切
...One Ring to find them...
至尊魔戒 调遗一切
...One Ring to bring them all...
至尊魔戒 召集一切
..and in the darkness bind them."
至尊魔戒 荐视一切
This is the One Ring...
它就是至尊魔戒
.. forged by the Dark Lord Sauron in the fires of Mount Doom.
是由黑暗魔君索伦 在末日山的烈焰中铸造的
Taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
埃西铎从索伦手中夺走了它
Bilbo found it.
比尔博发现了它
-In Gollum's cave. -Yes.
-在咕噜的山酒里 -是的
For 60 years, the Ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping...
60年来比尔搏一直藏在身边
... prolonging his life, delaying old age.
使他生命得以延续长生不老
But no longer, Frodo. Evil is stirring in Mordor.
现在不同了 佛罗多 魔多的政恶势力在森末和欲动
The Ring has awoken.
至尊魔戒已经苏醒
It's heard its master's call.
它听到了主人的召唤
But he was destroyed. Sauron was destroyed.
可它已经被消灭了 索伦已经被消灭了
No, Frodo.
没有 佛罗多
The spirit of Sauron endured.
索伦的灵魂并没有毁灭
His life force is bound to the Ring, and the Ring survived.
它把力量留给了魔戒 而魔戒残存下来
Sauron has returned.
索伦已经卷土重来
His Orcs have multiplied.
他的军队成倍增加
His fortress at Barad-ddr is rebuilt in the land of Mordor.
他已经在魔多国 重新建起他的城堡
Sauron needs only this Ring to cover all the lands in a second darkness.
索伦需要这枚至尊魔戒 来控制所有其它魔戒
He is seeking it.
他在搜寻至尊魔戒
Seeking it. All his thought is bent on it.
不顾一切地寻找它
For the Ring yearns above all else...
至尊魔戒也渴望着
.. to return to the hand of its master.
回到主人的手里
They are one...
他们是一体的
.. the Ring and the Dark Lord.
魔戒和魔君
Frodo...
佛罗多
..he must never find it.
绝对不能让他们找到它
All right.
那好吧
We put it away. We keep it hidden. We never speak of it again.
我们马上扔掉它 把它藏起来再也不提它
No one Knows it's here, do they?
没人知道它在这儿 对不对?
Do they, Gandalf?
对吗 甘道夫
There is one other who knew that Bilbo had the Ring.
还有一个人知道它在比尔博手里
I looked everywhere for the creature Gollum.
我想尽办法寻找那个小怪物咕噜
But the enemy found him first.
但是敌人先找到了他
! don't know how long they tortured him.
我不知道他们折磨他有多久
But amidst the endless screams and inane babble, they discerned two words:
但我知道为了达到日的 他们会不择手段
Shire!
夏尔
Baggins!
巴金斯
Shire.
夏尔国
Baggins. But that would lead them here!
巴金斯 他们肯定会找来
Who goes there?
什么人?
Take it, Gandalfl
拿去
-Take it! -No, Frodo.
-你拿去 - 不行
-You must take it! -You cannot offer me this ring!
=你一定要拿着 =- 你不能把这枚魔戒给我
-I'm giving it to you! -Don't tempt me, Frodo!
一我一定要给你 一不行 别让它靠近我
I dare not take it.
我不能要它
Not even to keep it safe.
这样不安全
Understand, Frodo...
知道吗 佛罗多
... would use this Ring from a desire to do good.
这枚魔戒会把我变成恶魔
But through me, it would wield a power too great and terrible to imagine.
通过我 它的魔力会 增加到难以想象的程度
-But it cannot stay in the Shire! -No.
-那也不能让它留在夏尔国 -不
No, it can't.
当然不能
What must I do?
我该做什么
-You must leave. And leave quickly. -Where? Where do ! go?
一你要离开这儿 马上走 -去哪儿 我该去哪儿
Get out of the Shire. Make for the village of Bree.
离开夏尔国 然后去布理
Bree.
布理
-What about you? -I'll be waiting for you...
一你怎么办? -我会在那儿等你
..at the inn of the Prancing Pony.
就在烈马酒吧
-And the Ring will be safe there? -I don't know, Frodo.
-魔戒在那里会安全吗 一不知道 佛罗多
I don't have any answers.
我也不知道
I must see the head of my order. He is both wise and powerful. Trust me, Frodo.
我要去见我的首领 他是个 智慧超凡的强人 相信我 佛罗多
He'll Know what to do.
你知道该怎么做
You'll have to leave the name of Baggins behind you.
不过你不能再姓巴金斯了
That name is not safe outside the Shire.
离开有夏尔国那个姓是很危险的
Travel only by day. And stay off the road.
你在路上必须隐姓埋名
I can cut across country easily enough.
为了夏尔国 我做什么都可以
My dear Frodo.
亲爱的佛罗多
Hobbits really are amazing creatures.
昨比特人真是有趣的生物
You can learn all that there is to know about their ways in a month.
你能在一个月内了解他们的一切
And yet, after a hundred years...
可是在1百年之后
.. they can still surprise you.
他们照样能使你大吃一惊
Get down.
趴下
Confound it all, Samwise Gamgee! Have you been eavesdropping?
你想干什么山姆怀斯 甘姆齐 在偷听我们谈话吗
I haven't been dropping no eaves. Honest. I was cutting the grass under the window.
我刚才没有偷听 我只不过 在修剪窗子下面的草坪
A little late for trimming the verge, don't you think?
你想用航草坪来蔬混过关
-l heard raised voices. -What did you hear? Speak!
=- 你让我把话说完 一你听到什么? 说
Nothing important.
没听到什么
That is, l heard a good deal about a ring, a Dark Lord and the end of the world but--
我只听到你们说什么戒指 还有敌人 还有比尔博先生
Please, Mr. Gandalf, sir, don't hurt me. Don't turn me into anything unnatural.
求你了甘道夫老他 我也是忍不住才想听听的
No?
没有
Perhaps not.
也许没有
I've thought of a better use for you.
不过我对你倒有别的意思
Come along, Samwise. Keep up.
快点 山姆 跟上
Be careful, both of you.
你们两个要多加小心
The enemy has many spies in his service:
敌人已派出许多耳日
Birds, beasts.
包括怪乌和怪兽
Is it safe?
魔戒安全了吗
Never put it on...
一刻也不要离身
.. for the agents of the Dark Lord will be drawn to its power.
黑暗魔君的手下会 被它的魔力吸引过来
Always remember, Frodo...
二万记住
.. the Ring is trying to get back to its master.
魔戒时刻想着要回到主人身边
It wants to be found.
它巴不得被人找到
This is it.
就是这儿了
This is what?
就是哪儿了?
If ltake one more step...
只要我再迈一步
.. it'll be the farthest away from home I've ever been.
就会离开生我养我的家乡了
Come on, Sam.
来吧 山姆
Remember what Bilbo used to say:
别忘了比尔博经常说的话
-"It's a dangerous business, Frodo." -"Going out your door.
-走出你的家门是件很危险的事 一佛罗多 一旦走上这条路
You step onto the road, and if you don't keep your feet...
如果管不住自己的双腿
... there's no Knowing where you might be swept off fo."
简直就不知道会滑到什么地方
Smoke rises from the Mountain of Doom.
末日山脉冒着滚滚浓烟
The hour grows fate.
时间已经很晚了
And Gandalf the Grey rides to isengard...
甘道夫终于赶到艾辛格
... seeking my counsel.
寻求我的帮助
For that is why you have come, is it not?
你是为那件事来找我的 对吗
My old friend.
我的老友
Saruman.
萨重曼
-You are sure of this? -Beyond any doubt.
-这都是真的吗 一于真万确
So the Ring of Power has been found.
这人么说至尊魔戒真的找到了
All these long years, it was in the Shire.
这些年它一直藏在夏尔国
-Under my very nose. -Yet you did not have the wit to see it.
一就在我眼皮底下 = 而你却浑然不知
Your love of the halfling's leaf has clearly slowed your mind.
显然你对需比特族烟叶的热衷 遮芒了你的双眼
But we still have time. Time enough to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
不过我们还有时间 如果马上行动 就有足够时间对付索伦
Time?
时间?
What time do you think we have?
你认为我们还有了时间?
Sauron has regained much of his former strength.
索伦的魔力已经基本恢复
He cannot yet take physical form...
尽管眼下他还不能显形
...but his spirit has lost none of its potency.
但他的精神力量已经完好如初
Concealed within his fortress, the Lord of Mordor sees all.
这个魔多的君王躲在 他的城堡里备视着一切
His gaze pierces cloud, shadow, earth and flesh.
他的日光能够穿透乌云 黑暗 大地和血肉之躯
You know of what I speak, Gandalf.
你明白我的意思吗 甘道夫
A Great Eye, lidless, wreathed in flame.
那只没有眼瞪的眼睛闪烁着火光
The Eye of Sauron.
是的 索伦
He is gathering all evil to him.
他把所有的那恶集于一身
Very soon, he'll have summoned an army great enough for an assault upon Middle-earth.
他很快能召集起强大的大军 向中土发起进攻
You know this?
你怎么知道?
How?
怎么会?
I have seen it.
我亲眼所见
A palantir is a dangerous tool, Saruman.
使用水晶魔石非常危险
Why?
为什么?
Why should we fear to use it?
我们为什么不敢使用水晶魔石
They are not all accounted for, the lost Seeing-stones.
因为其中一块水晶魔石已经丢失
We do not know who else may be watching.
别人也会用它来观察我们
The hour is later than you think.
总之我们已经回天无术
Sauron's forces are already moving.
索伦的军队已经开始行动
The Nine have left Minas Morgul.
丸大戒灵已经离开米那斯魔窟
The Nine?
戒灵?
They crossed the River Isen on Midsummer's Eve...
他们在仲夏夜前跨过了大河
... disguised as riders in black.
都装扮成黑衣骑士的模样
-They've reached the Shire? -They will find the Ring.
-进入起比特? =-他们会找到至尊魔戒
And kill the one who carries it.
并且会杀死它的持有者
Frodo!
佛罗多
You did not seriously think that a Hobbit could contend with the will of Sauron?
你不会真的以为袁比特人能 抵抗索伦的意志吧
There are none who can.
为没有人能够做到
Against the power of Mordor...
与魔多的势力对抗
.. there can be no victory.
不可能取胜
We must join with him, Gandalf.
我们只能和他联手 甘道夫
We must join with Sauron.
我们只能臣服于索伦
It would be wise, my friend.
别无选择 我的朋友
Tell me...
告诉我
.. friend...
朋友
.. when did Saruman the Wise abandon reason for madness?
智者萨重曼什么时候弃明投暗了
I gave you the chance...
我的本意是想给你机会
...of aiding me willingly...
帮助我
...but you have elected the way of pain!
没想到你敬酒不吃吃罚酒
Mr. Frodo?
佛罗多老人区 佛罗多
-l thought I'd lost you. -What are you talking about?
一我还以为失去你了 -你瞎想什么
-It's just something Gandalf said. -What did he say?
-我在想革道夫说过的话 一他说了什么
"Don't you lose him, Samwise Gamgee." And don't mean to.
不要把他弄委了 山姆 我不想失去你
Sam, we're still in the Shire. What could possibly happen?
山姆 我们还在夏尔国内 怎么会发生意外呢
Frodo.
-是佛罗多 梅里 是佛罗多 一你好 佛罗多
Get off him.
靠边站
Come on, Frodo.
走吧 佛罗多
What's the meaning of this?
这是怎么回事?
You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
你们在偷马嘎的庄稼
You get back here!
找小子 从我的地里滚出去
Get out of my field!
滚出去 臭小子
You know what's gonna happen when I catch up with you?
滚出去 滚出去
I don't know why he's so upset. It's only a couple of carrots.
他和干吗发那么大火 不过是几根胡葛小而已
And some cabbages.
再加上几棵圆白菜
And those three bags of potatoes that we lifted last week.
还有上星期的几袋子士豆
-And then the mushrooms the week before. -Yes, Pippin. My point is...
-和上上星期的那些蘑菇 -没错 皮平
.. he's clearly overreacting.
他简直是太过分了
Run!
快跑
Oh, that was close.
真是太悬了
I think I've broken something.
我好像弄断了什么
Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
这都怪巴克和图克家的人
What? That was just a detour. A shortcut.
怎么回事? 我们好像因祸得福了
-Shortcut to what? -Mushrooms!
一得什么福? -是蘑菇
That's mine.
别动 那是我的
That's nice, Merry.
太好了 梅里
Here's a nice one, Sam.
这蘑菇真漂亮 山姆
I think we should get off the road.
我想咱们应该藏起来
Get off the road!
快点藏起来
Quick!
快
Be quiet!
不要出声
What was that?
那是什么
Anything?
有情况吗
Nothing.
没有
What is going on?
这是怎么回事?
That Black Rider was looking for something. Or someone.
那个黑骑士在找东西 或是在找人
Get down!
趴下
I have to leave the Shire.
我得离开夏尔国
Sam and! must get to Bree.
山姆和我必须去布理
Right.
好吧
Bucklebury Ferry. Follow me.
走巴寇伯理渡口最近 跟我来
Run!
快跑
This way! Follow me!
跟我来
Get the rope, Sam!
摘掉缆绳 山姆
Frodo!
佛罗多 快跑 佛罗多
Gol -Hurry!
一快跑 一快点
-Come on! Faster! -Jump!
一跳呀
-How far to the nearest crossing? -The Brandywine Bridge. 20 miles.
一下一个渡口还有多运 -有烈酒桥 还有12英里
Come on.
快点
-What do you want? -We're heading for the Prancing Pony.
=你们有什么事 =我们要找烈马酒吧
Hobbits. Four Hobbits!
昨比特人 四个需比特人
-What business brings you to Bree? -We wish to stay at the inn.
一你们为什么来布理? =-我们想借酒馆歇脚
Our business is our own.
别的事与你无关
All right, young sir. I meant no offense.
好吧 年轻的老爷 我没别的意思
It's my job to ask questions after nightfall.
我的职责就是天黑后进行盘查
There's talk of strange folk abroad.
听说这一带有陌生人出没
Can't be too careful.
小心总没大错
Out of the way! Watch where you're walking.
快内开 走路看着点
Excuse me.
对不起
Good evening, little masters.
晚上好 矮人老公
If you're seeking accommodation, we got some cozy Hobbit-sized rooms available.
如果你们想找住处 我们这里有和舒适的矮人房间
Mister...?
请问贵姓
Underhill. My name's Underhill.
山下 我姓山下
-Undernhill, yes. -We're friends of Gandalf the Grey.
-山下 =我们是灰袍巫师甘道夫的朋友
-Can you tell him we've arrived? -Gandalf?
一能通报一声吗 一甘道夫?
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Big grey beard, pointy hat.
长着灰色大胡子 戴着尖项帆
Not seen him for six months.
有半年没见到他了
What do we do now?
我们怎么办?
Sam...
山姆
.. he'll be here. He'll come.
他会来的 一定会
Get out of my way!
别挡道
What's that?
那是什么
This, my friend, is a pint.
我的朋友 这是酒杯
It comes in pints?
用来盛酒的?
-I'm getting one. -You got a whole half already!
-那我也来一杯 一你已经喝了半杯了
That fellow's done nothing but stare at you since we arrived.
我们进来后那家伙一直在采着你
Excuse me.
对不起
That Man in the corner. Who is he?
墙角那个人 他是谁?
He's one of them Rangers. They're dangerous folk, wandering the Wilds.
他是个巡林人是个危险人物 整天在森林里游水
What his right name is, I've never heard, but around here he's known as Strider.
我不知道他叫什么 不过在这一带人们都叫他健步侠
Strider.
健步侠
Baggins.
巴金斯
He's over there. Frodo Baggins.
就在那边 他叫佛罗多“' 巴金斯
He's my second cousin, once removed on his mother's side...
是我的第一代表兄弟 我们的母亲是亲姐妹
..and my third cousin, twice removed....
也是我的第二代堂兄弟 我们的爷爷是亲兄弟
-Pippin! -Steady on, Frodo.
-皮平 一悠着点
You cannot hide.
你无处可藏
I see you.
我能看到你
There is no life...
虚空的世界
.. in the void.
没有生命
Only...
只有
... death.
死亡
You draw far too much attention to yourself, "Mr. Underhill."
你未兔太招摇了 我的山下老仓
What do you want?
-你想干什么 -小心 你戴的东西不是闹着玩的
-l carry nothing. -Indeed.
一我什么也没戴 一是吗
I can avoid being seen if! wish...
如果我想躲起来也能做到
...but to disappear entirely, that is a rare gift.
但若想彻底消失可没那么容易
-Who are you? -Are you frightened?
-你是谁 一紧张了?
Yes.
是的
Not nearly frightened enough. I Know what hunts you.
你还不够紧张 我知道找你的人是谁
Let him go! Or I'll have you, Longshanks.
你放开他 不然我让你好看 大个子
You have a stout heart, little Hobbit. But that will not save you.
昨比特矮人 胆子不小 不过只有胆子救不了你
You can no longer wait for the wizard, Frodo.
你不能再等焉师了
They're coming.
他们就来
What are they?
他们是谁?
They were once Men.
曾经是人类
Great kings of Men.
部族的首领
Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them nine rings of power.
后来大骗子索伦 把9枚魔戒送给了他们
Blinded by their greed, they took them without question.
由于贪楚他们想都没想就收下了
One by one, falling into darkness.
结果一个一个圣入深渊
Now they are slaves to his will.
变成了索伦的奴仆
They are the Nazg(l.
他们是戒灵
Ringwraiths. Neither living nor dead.
魔戒的阴魂 介于生死之间
At all times they feel...
他们能感知
... the presence of the Ring...
魔戒的存在
... drawn to the power of the One. They will never stop hunting you.
无时无刻不在追踪魔式的踪迹 他们永远对你穷追不舍
-Where are you taking us? -Into the Wild.
一我们去哪儿? -森林里
How do we know this Strider is a friend of Gandalf?
我们怎么知道这个健步侠 是不是甘道夫的朋友
We have no choice but to trust him.
可除此之外 我们别无选择
-But where is he leading us? -To Rivendell, Master Gamgee.
一他要带我们去哪儿 一瑞文鼓尔 甘姆齐老爷
-To the house of Elrond. -Did you hear that? Rivendell.
一到爱隆家去 =你们听到了吗? 瑞文戴尔
Were going to see the Elves.
我们要去看精灵了
-Gentlemen, we do not stop till nightfall. -What about breakfast?
-先生们 天黑前我们不能停下 -那早饭该怎么办
-You've already had it. -We've had one, yes.
一你吃过了 -我们是吃过了第一餐
What about second breakfast?
可是我们的第二餐呢
Don't think he knows about second breakfast, Pip.
别指望他知道第二顿早饭
What about elevenses? Luncheon? Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper?
还有上午茶呢? 还有午饭 下午茶 晚餐 宵夜
-He knows about them, doesn't he? -l wouldn't count on it.
-这些他都知道吗 -我看希望不大
Pippin!
帮帮有我 皮平
The power of isengard is at your command...
大地之王索伦
... Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
艾伴格听候你的调谴
Build me an army worthy of Mordor.
你要为我建立一支 不辱魔多使命的军队
What orders from Mordor, my lord? What does the Eye command?
魔多方面要我们做什么 我的主人 他下了命令吗
We have work to do.
我们有事情做了
The trees are strong, my lord. Their roots go deep.
这些树很粗壮 根深蒂
Rip them all down.
给我全部推倒
This was the great watchtower of Amon Sal.
这是山上最高的卡望塔
We shall rest here tonight.
今晚在这儿过夜
These are for you. Keep them close.
拿着这个 时刻不能离身
I'm going to have a look around.
我去周围看看
Stay here.
等在这儿
My tomato's burst.
我的攻茵有裂开了
Could ! have some bacon?
我来点是猪肉好吗
Want a tomato, Sam?
要蕃茄吗
-What are you doing?! -Tomatoes, sausages, nice crispy bacon.
=-你们在干什么 -蕃茄 香肠 好吃的量猪肉
-We saved some for you, Mr. Frodo. -Put it out, you fools!
一我们给你留了一些 -把火灭掉 傻瓜
-Put it out! -That's nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
瞧你干的好事 把我的蕃茄弄脏了
Gol
快走
Back, you devils!
滚回去 魔鬼
Frodo!
佛罗多
Strider!
健步侠
-Help him, Strider. -He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade.
-健步侠 一他是被魔写剑刺伤的
This is beyond my skill to heal. He needs Elvish medicine.
我的医术无能为力 只有精灵能救他
Hurry!
快点
We're six days from Rivendell! He'll never make it!
我们距瑞文戴尔还有 6天的路程 他坚持不到
Hold on, Frodo.
坚持住 佛罗多
Gandalfl
甘道夫
Mr. Frodo? He's going cold.
佛罗多老爷 他快不行了
Is he going to die?
他会不会死?
He's passing into the Shadow World. He'll soon become a Wraith like them.
他正在去阴界的路上 很快也会成为戒灵的
-They're close. -Sam, do you know the Athelas plant?
一他们在附近? -山姆 你知道阿夕拉斯植物吗
-Athelas? -Kingsfoil.
一阿夕拉斯? 一也叫金丝泪
Kingsfoil, aye, it's a weed.
那是一种草
It may help to slow the poisoning. Hurry!
它能够缓解毒性 快去
What's this? A Ranger caught off his guard?
怎么了 一个游侠竟会束手就擒?
Frodo.
佛罗多
Who is she?
她是谁?
-She's an Elf. -He's fading.
一她是精灵 一他快不行了
He's not going to last.
他坚持不了多入
We must get him to my father.
我们必须要带他去见我父亲
-I've been looking for you for two days. -Where are you taking him?
一我已经找了你们整整两天 一你要带他去哪儿?
There are five Wraiths behind you. Where the other four are, I do not know.
有5个戒灵他们正在追你们 另外4个不知去向
What are they saying?
他们在说什么?
I do not fear them.
我不怕那些戒灵
Arwen...
一路顺风
...fide hard. Don't look back.
快马加办 别回头
What are you doing?! Those Wraiths are still out there!
你们想干什么 那些戒灵就在附近
Give up the halfling, She-Elf.
把那矮人交给我
If you want him, come and claim him.
如果你们想要 那就过来吧
No. No!
不不
Frodo, no.
佛罗多
Frodo, don't give in.
佛罗多 不要放弃
Not now.
坚持住
What grace is given me...
上帝 请把你对我的恩典
...let it pass to him.
全部转给佛罗多
Let him be spared.
让他得救吧
Save him.
请救救他
-Where am I? -You are in the house of Elrond.
一我在哪儿 -你在爱隆家
And it is 10:00 in the morning on October 24th, if you want to know.
如果你想知道的话 现在是10月24日上午10点
-Gandalfl -Yes, l'm here.
一鞭道夫 -是 是我
And you're lucky to be here too.
幸亏你及时来到这里
A few more hours and you would have been beyond our aid.
再晚几个小时我们就救不了你了
But you have some strength in you, my dear Hobbit.
不过你非常坚强 替比特人
What happened, Gandalf?
出了什么事 甘道夫
-Why didn't you meet us? -lam sorry, Frodo.
一你为什么不去见我们 一对不起 佛罗多
I was delayed.
我有事耽搁了
A friendship with Saruman is not lightly thrown aside.
萨鲁曼不是轻易放弃友情的人
One ill turn deserves another. It is over.
人们经常说祸不单行
Embrace the power of the Ring...
你大势已去 拥抱力量魔戒吧
...or embrace your own destruction!
否则你必有死无疑
There is only one Lord of the Ring.
至尊魔戒只有一位主人
Only one who can bend it to his will.
只有那个人可以控制它的意志
And he does not share power.
但那人是个独裁者
So you have chosen death.
这么说你选择死蕊
Gandalf? What is it?
甘道夫 怎么了
Nothing, Frodo.
没什么 佛罗多
Frodo!
佛罗多
-Sam. -Bless you, you're awake!
-山姆 一谢天谢地你终于醒了
Sam has hardly left your side.
山姆一直陪在你身边
We were that worried about you. Weren't we, Mr. Gandalf?
我们真为你担心 是吧 甘道夫老分
By the skills of Lord Elrond, you're beginning to mend.
赁着爱隆的医术你的伤口开始愈合
Welcome to Rivendell, Frodo Baggins.
欢迎来到瑞文戴尔 佛罗多“' 巴金斯
-Bilbo! -Hello, Frodo, my lad.
一比尔博 一你好 佛罗多 我的孩子
"There and Back Again:
《去而复归》
A Hobbit's Tale, by Bilbo Baggins."
才比特族的故事 作者比尔博' 巴金斯
-This is wonderful. -I meant to go back...
一太好了 一我想回去
.. wonder at the powers of Mirkwood...
我怀念黑森林的雄浑
... visit Lake-town...
我想去拜访湖城
...8ee the Lonely Mountain again.
想再看看独峰山
But age, it seems, has finally caught up with me.
可是我老了 这回真的老了
I miss the Shire.
我想念夏尔国
I spent all my childhood pretending I was off somewhere else.
我小时候一直都梦想 自己能够在外面闯荡
Off with you, on one of your adventures.
跟够和你一起到处历险
But my own adventure turned out to be quite different.
可是我自己的探险经历却完全不同
I'm not like you, Bilbo.
我和你不一样 比尔博
My dear boy.
我的好孩子
-Now, what have ! forgotten? -Packed already?
一我没扎什么东西吧? 一已经开始准备了?
No harm in being prepared.
有备无患嘛
-l thought you wanted to see the Elves. -l do.
一我记得你一直想看精灵 一没错
-More than anything. -I did.
- 而且特别想
It's just...
只不过
We did what Gandalf wanted, didn't we?
这一切都是甘道夫安排的 对吗
We got the Ring this far, to Rivendell. And I thought...
我们千里运迅把魔戒带到瑞文戴尔
..8eeing as how you're on the mend, we'd be off soon.
一旦你的伤好了 我们就得上路
Off home.
返回家乡
You are right, Sam.
你说对了 山姆
We did what we set out to do.
我们实现了来这儿的日的
The Ring will be safe in Rivendell.
至苯魔戒在这儿会很安全
lam ready to go home.
我也做好了回家的准备
His strength returns.
他的体力恢复了
And yet to have come so far still bearing the Ring...
路途遥遥他始终把魔戒带在身上
.. the Hobbit has shown extraordinary resilience to its evil.
昨比特族对魔戒的政恶 有超强的抵御能力
It is a burden he should never have had to bear.
佛罗多不应承受这样的重负
-We can ask no more of Frodo. -Gandalf, the enemy is moving.
=我们不能再要求他做什么 一甘道夫 敌人正在行动
Sauron's forces are massing in the East. His Eye is fixed on Rivendell.
索伦的军队来到了东方 他的日光采着瑞文戴尔
And Saruman, you tell me, has betrayed us.
而且你说萨鲁曼已经背关了我们
Our list of allies grows thin.
我们的同盟者所剩无几
His treachery runs deeper than you know.
他的叛变比你想象得还要糟糕
By foul craft, Saruman has crossed Orcs with Goblin-men.
萨鲁曼利用那恶魔力 实现了夜精灵和妖人的混血杂交
He's breeding an army in the caverns of Isengard.
他正在制造军队
An army that can move in sunlight and cover great distance at speed.
可以在光天化日之下长途奔次
Saruman is coming for the Ring.
日的是夺取至尊魔戒
This evil cannot be concealed by the power of the Elves.
我们精灵的力量无法镇住魔式的收恶
We do not have the strength to fight both Mordor and Isengard!
我们也无法同时抗衡魔多和艾辛格
Gandalf...
甘道夫
.. the Ring cannot stay here.
魔戒不能留在这里
This peril belongs to all Middle-earth.
整个中土世界都危在旦夕
They must decide now how fo end it
大家必须商讨对策
The time of the Elves is over. My people are leaving these shores.
精灵的时代就要过去 我的人正在离开河岸
Who will you look to when we've gone? The Dwarves?
等我们走光了 你还投靠谁 侏儒族?
They hide in mountains seeking riches. They care not for the troubles of others.
他们只会躲在山酒里 从来不关心别人的事情
It is in Men that we must place our hope.
我们只能把希望寄托在人类身上
Men?
人类?
Men are weak. The race of Men is failing.
他们太软弱 他们的种族正在误落
The blood of Numencr is all but spent, its pride and dignity forgotten.
他们的热血已经变冷 他们的骄傲和尊严未失殉尽
It is because of Men the Ring survives.
因为人类才使至尊魔戒留到现在
l was there, Gandalf.
我去过那儿 甘道夫
! was there 3000 years ago...
3千年以前
... when Isildur took the Ring.
埃西铎夺取至尊魔式的时候
I was there the day the strength of Men failed.
人类开始训败的时候我也在那里
Isildur, hurry! Follow me.
埃西铎 快点 跟我来
led Isifdur into the heart of Mount Doom...
我领着埃西铎来到 末日山的心脏地带
... where the Ring was forged, the one place it could be destroyed.
也就是打造至尊魔戒 和销毁至尊魔戒的地方
Cast it into the fire!
把它扔进火里
-Destroy it! -No.
-毁掉它 -不
Isildur!
埃西铎
It should have ended that day, but evil was allowed to endure.
那天本是政恶的末日 但它却得以苟延残喘
Isildur kept the Ring. The line of kings is broken.
埃西铎留下了至尊魔戒 王国的血脉被断送了
There's no strength left in the world of Men.
人类从此失去了力量变得四分五裂
-They're scattered, divided, leaderless. -There is one who could unite them.
=分崩离析群龙无首 -阿拉贡可以把他们联合起来
One who could reclaim the throne of Gondor.
他完全有能力重振国威
He turned from that path a long time ago.
很早以前他就放弃了这种打算
He has chosen exile.
他选择了流亡生活
The shards of Narsil.
纳希尔圣剑
The blade that cut the Ring from Sauron's hand.
是你砍下了索伦的魔戒
It's still sharp.
你还是那么锋利
But no more than a broken heirloom.
可是已无人继承
Why do you fear the past?
你为什么害怕过去
You are Isildur's heir, not Isildur himself.
你不是埃西色 你只是他的继承人
You are not bound to his fate.
你不会重蹈他的克国
The same blood flows in my veins.
我的血脉中流着同样的血液
The same weakness.
同样软弱
Your time will come.
你迟早要承担重任
You will face the same evil. And you will defeat it.
夯对同样的政恶 你一定能打败它
You said you'd bind yourself to me...
我记得你说你愿意嫁给我
.. forsaking the immortal life of your people.
不异放弃自己永生的神仙生活
And to that I hold.
对此我至今不悔
I would rather share one lifetime with you...
我和你相守虽然只能生活一世
.. than face all the Ages of this world alone.
却胜过仙境空守独闺万年
I choose a mortal life.
我宁愿过凡人的日子
-You cannot give me this. -It is mine to give to whom I will...
-我不值得你这样做 一我愿意把自己献给
.. like my heart.
我心爱的人
Strangers from distant lands, friends of old...
各位远道而来的新朋老友
.. you've been summoned here to answer the threat of Mordor.
这次召集你们来 是为了对付魔多的威胁
Middle-earth stands upon the brink of destruction. None can escape it.
中土世界已经到了最后的关头 无人可以幸免
You will unite, or you will fall.
要么团结起来 要么一起灭亡
Each race is bound to this fate, this one doom.
无论哪个种族都面临着 同样的命运和劫难
Bring forth the Ring, Frodo.
把至尊魔戒拿出来 佛罗多
So it is true.
原来是真的
-The doom of Man. -Itis a gift.
-至尊魔式 人类的蛋运 -它是上帝的礼物
A gift to the foes of Mordor.
是对抗魔多的法宝
Why not use this Ring?
我们为什么不利用它呢
Long has my father, the Steward of Gondor...
我的父亲是刚铎的总管
... kept the forces of Mordor at bay. By the blood of our people...
他一直在魔多的军队作战 正是我们的浴血奋战
..are your lands kept safe.
才使你们的土地安享太平
Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy. Let us use it against him.
应该把敌人的武器交给刚色 用它来以牙还牙
You cannot wield it. None of us can.
你们无法控制它 我们大家谁都不能
The One Ring answers to Sauron alone. It has no other master.
至苯魔戒是只听从索伦的旨意 它只有一个主人
And what would a Ranger know of this matter?
一个巡林人何以会知道这些事情?
This is no mere Ranger.
他不是普通的巡林人
He is Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
他是阿拉贡 阿拉松的儿子
You owe him your allegiance.
你们都应该效忠于他
Aragorn.
阿拉贡
This is Isildur's heir?
他就是埃西铎的后裔
And heir to the throne of Gondor.
刚铎王位的继承人
Gondor has no king.
刚铎没有国王
Gondor needs no king.
刚铎不需要国王
Aragorn is right. We cannot use it.
阿拉贡说得对 我们不能使用它
You have only one choice.
你们只有一个选择
The Ring must be destroyed.
必须毁掉至尊魔戒
What are we waiting for?
那我 们还等什么?
The Ring cannot be destroyed, Gimli, son of Gldin...
葛罗音的儿子金需 利用我们现有的手段
...by any craft that we here possess.
至苯魔戒是无法毁掉的
The Ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom.
它在末日山的烈焰中打造
Only there can it be unmade.
也只能去那里把它销毁
It must be taken deep into Mordor...
必须把它带到魔多的腹地
..and cast back into the fiery chasm from whence it came.
再把它扔进那个锻造它的烈焰峡谷之中
One of you...
你们必须
...must do this.
做这事
One does not simply walk into Mordor.
去魔多的领地可没那么简单
Its Black Gates are guarded by more than just Orcs.
半兽人把守着那扇黑色大门
There is evil there that does not sleep.
还有恶魔昼夜看守
The Great Eye is ever-watchful.
索伦的巨眼也采着那里
It is a barren wasteland...
那是一片不毛之地
..fiddled with fire, and ash and dust.
筹罩在浓烟烈火和灰坚之中
The very air you breathe iS a poisonous fume.
可供呼吸的只有毒气
Not with 10,000 men could you do this. It is folly.
没有十万人你休想靠近那里 白日做梦
Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said? The Ring must be destroyed.
爱隆的话你一句也没听进去吗
And if we fail, what then? What happens when Sauron takes back what is his?
如果我们失败了怎么办 如果索伦把他的魔戒抢走怎么办
I will be dead before I see the Ring in the hands of an Elfl
说什么也不能让至尊魔戒 留在精灵人手里
Never trust an Elfl
精灵都不可靠
Do you not understand? While you bicker amongst yourselves, Sauron's power grows!
大家还不明折吗? 在你们争吵 不体时 索伦的势力正在壮大
None can escape it! You'll all be destroyed!
所有的人都在友难逃 你们都将被消灭
I will take it.
让我去做吧
I will take the Ring to Mordor.
让我带着魔戒去魔多
Though...
尽管
.... do not know the way.
我不认识去那里的路
[ will help you bear this burden, Frodo Baggins...
如果虫你持有魔戒的话 佛罗多“' 巴金斯
..as long as it is yours to bear.
我会帮助你完成重任
If by my life or death I can protect you...
如果能用生命来捍卫你
.L will,
我在所不辞
You have my sword.
我的剑听你调谴
And you have my bow.
我的弓听候你调谴
And my ax.
还有我的利斧
You carry the fates of us alll, little one.
中土的命运担在你肩上
If this is indeed the will of the Council...
如果理事会一臻通过
.. then Gondor will see it done.
刚铎会助你一臂之力
-Frodo's not going anywhere without me. -It is hardly possible to separate you...
佛罗多老爷去哪儿都会带着我
... even when he is summoned to a secret Council and you are not.
尽管他参加了秘密理事会 而你没有参加
We're coming too!
我们也要去 谁也阻止不了我们
You'll have to send us home tied up in a sack to stop us.
除韭你们把我们塞进麻袋里
Anyway, you need people of intelligence on this sort of...
总之完成这样的使命 没有聪明人帮助
woe Mission.
可不行
Quest.
请你们
Thing.
答应
Well, that rules you out, Pip.
其实你并不聪明
Nine companions.
一共9位
So be it.
就这样吧
You shall be the Fellowship of the Ring.
你们就是护戒使者
Great!
太好了
Where are we going?
我们要去哪儿
My old sword!
我的看家宝剑
Sting.
刺针
Here, take it. Take it.
拿着 拿着
-It's so light. -Yes. Made by the Elves, you know.
一它韭常轻 -是的 因为是由精灵人制造的
The blade glows blue when Orcs are close.
遇到半兽人时剑刃会发光
And it's times like that, my lad, when you have to be extra careful.
当它发出光芒的时候 你就要格 外小心 了
Here's a pretty thing.
还有一件宝物
Mithril.
银甲
As light as a feather, and as hard as dragon scales.
它轻如羽毛 坚固如龙甲
Let me see you put it on. Come on.
穿起来让我看看 来吧
My old ring.
我的宝贝魔戒
I should very much like...
我真想
...to hold it again, one last time.
再最后一次看它一眼
I'm sorry ! brought this upon you, my boy.
对不起 我给你车麻烦了
I'm sorry that you must carry this burden.
让你背上了这么大的包袜
I'm sorry for everything.
我真的很对不起
We must hold to this course, west of the Misty Mountains, for 40 days.
我们必须沿着这条路 在雾灵山向西走40天
if our luck holds, the Gap of Rohan will still be open to us.
如果一切顺利我们就可以
From there, our road turns east to Mordor.
再从那里往东直奔魔多
Two, one, five. Good! Very good.
很好 好极了 再来
Move your feet.
当心你的脚
-You look good, Pippin. -Thanks.
-二得不错 皮和平 一谢谢
Faster!
来吧
If anyone was to ask for my opinion, which I note they're not...
如果有谁征求我的意见 当然 没人那么做
.. I'd say we were taking the long way round.
我会说 咱们舍近求远了
Gandalf, we could pass through the Mines of Moria.
甘道夫 我们完全可以穿过摩瑞亚山洞
My cousin Balin would give us a royal welcome.
我表弟巴林会热烈欢迎我们
No, I would not take the road through Moria unless I had no other choice.
不 除非万不得已 我不会选择穿过摩瑞亚山洞
Sorry!
二一五很好 对不起
Get him!
捉住他
-For the Shire! -Hold him. Hold him down, Merry!
把他压住
You've got my arm!
你压住我有拘膊了
-What is that? -Nothing. It's just a wisp of cloud.
-那是什么 一不过是一片乌云
It's moving fast.
移动非常快
-Crebain from Dunland! -Hide!
-登兰德山谷的间谍乌巫 一隐蔽
-Hurry! -Take cover!
快 快藏起来
Spies of Saruman.
它们是萨兽曼的侦探
The passage south is being watched.
向南的路已被封锁
We must take the Pass of Caradhras.
只能改道卡兰德克拉斯山口
Frodo!
当心 佛罗多
Boromir.
博罗米尔
It is a strange fate that we should suffer so much fear and doubt...
真奇怪我们整天提心品胆担惊受怕
..over so small a thing.
就为了这小小的魔戒
Such a little thing.
这小东西
Boromir!
博罗米尔
Give the Ring to Frodo.
把魔戒还给佛罗多
As you wish.
遵命
I care not.
我无所谓
So, Gandalf, you tried to lead them over Caradhras.
甘道夫 这么说 你想带他们 穿越卡兰德克拉斯
And if that fails, where then will you go?
如果不行的话 你还能去哪儿呢
lf the mountain defeats you...
要是越不过那座山峰
... Will you risk a more dangerous road?
你们还会走更危险的路线吗
There is a fell voice on the air.
空中有一种可怕的声音
It's Saruman!
那是萨曾曼
He's trying to bring down the mountain! Gandalf, we must turn back!
萨重曼在制造山崩 甘道夫 我们必须回去
No!
不
We must get off the mountain!
我们必须下山
Make for the Gap of Rohan, and take the west road to my city!
还是走罗罕关隘吧 走西谷去我的家乡
The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to Isengard!
走罗罕天隘离艾辛格太近了
We cannot pass over a mountain. Let us go under it.
要是不能从山上通过 那就从山底下走
Let us go through the Mines of Moria.
我们可以穿越摩瑞亚山洞
Moria. You fear to go into those mines.
摩瑞亚山酒? 你们没有 胆量进入那些山酒
The Dwarves delved too greedily and too deep.
贪楚的侏儒 他们的山酒深不可测
You know what they awoke in the darkness of Khazad-dim:
谁知道他们在 阴暗的酒底唤醒了什么
Shadow and flame.
炎魔妖怪
Let the Ring-bearer decide.
那就让持戒人决定吧
Frodo?
佛罗多
We will go through the mines.
我们选择穿越山酒
So be it.
我同意
The walls...
那是摩瑞亚
...0f Moria.
山墙
Well, let's see.
让我想想
Ithildin.
伊希尔丁
It mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
它只在星光和月光下显现
It reads, "The Doors of Durin, Lord of Moria.
上面写的是 都灵之门 摩瑞亚之王
-Speak, friend, and enter." -What do you suppose that means?
一说声明友即可进入 -那上面说的是什么意思
It's simple. If you are a friend, you speak the password and the doors will open.
非常简单 只要是朋友 说出口令门就会打开
Mines are no place for a pony.
尽管比尔韭常勇敢
-Even one so brave as Bill. -Bye-bye, Bill.
-可山洞里走不了马 一再见了 比尔
Go on, Bill. Go on.
去吧 比尔 去吧
Don't worry, Sam, he knows the way home.
别担心 山姆 它认识回家的路
Do not disturb the water.
不要惊动湖水
Oh, it's useless.
我想想
It's a riddle.
一个谜语
"Speak friend! and enter."
说声朋友即可进入
What's the Elvish word for "friend"?
精灵语的“朋友”怎么说?
Soon, Master Elf, you will enjoy the fabled hospitality of the Dwarves.
精灵王 你很快就能 享受侏儒的热情款待了
Roaring fires, malt beer, ripe meat off the bone!
能能的答火 麦芽酒 美味的脱骨烤肉
This, my friend, is the home of my cousin Balin.
我有朋友 这是我表弟巴林的家
And they call it a mine.
他们管它叫矿酒
A mine!
一座矿泪
This is no mine. It's a tomb.
这不是矿酒 是坟
No...
不
Goblins.
是半兽人
We make for the Gap of Rohan. We should never have come here.
我们还是应该走罗罕关隘 就不应该来这儿
Now, get out of here. Get out!
快离开这儿 快离开
-Frodo! -Help!
一佛罗多 佛罗多 - 救我
Strider!
健步侠
-Get off him!
=- 放开他
Aragorn!
阿拉贡
Frodo!
佛罗多
Into the mines!
快进矿酒
-Legolas! -Into the cave!
一著戈拉斯 一到油里去
Run!
快跑
We must face the long dark of Moria.
只能穿过摩瑞亚山洞
Be on your guard.
大家要当心
There are older and fouler things than Orcs...
在地下更深处
...in the deep places of the world.
还有比半兽人更加阴险毒辣的东西
Quietly now. It's a four-day journey to the other side.
大家听着 我们得 用4天的时间才能走到头
Let us hope that our presence may go unnoticed.
但愿没人注意我们在这里
Pippin.
皮平
have no memory of this place.
我怎么会没有印象了
-Are we lost? -No.
一我们迷路了? 一没有
-[ think we are. -Gandalfs thinking.
一我看是迷路了 一甘道夫在思考呢
-Merry? -What?
一梅里 -干吗
I'm hungry.
我饿了
-There's something down there. -It's Gollum.
一下面有什么东西 -那是咕噜
-Gollum? -He's been following us for three days.
=- 咕噜? 一他已经跟了我们3天了
-He escaped the dungeons of Barad-diir? -Escaped...
-他从索伦的地牢里逃出来了? 一逃出来
...of was set loose.
或者是放出来
He hates and loves the Ring, as he hates and loves himself.
他对至尊魔戒爱恨交加 就像对他自己一样
He will never be rid of his need for it.
他永远不会放弃追踪至尊魔戒
It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him when he had the chance.
可情当初比尔博没有趁机杀死他
Pity?
可情?
It is pity that stayed Bilbo's hand.
比尔博出于怜帆才没有那样做
Many that live deserve death. Some that die deserve life.
很多活着的人该死 很多死去的人该生
Can you give it to them, Frodo?
你能让死者复活吗
Do not be too eager to deal out death and judgment.
不要急于做最后的审判
Even the very wise cannot see all ends.
即便最贤明的人 也说不出所有人的归宿
My heart tells me that Gollum has some part to play yet, for good or ill...
我的直沉告诉我咕噜还有用场 不管是好是坏
... before this is over.
他的戏还没有演完
The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
比尔博的怜帆决定着很多人的命运
I wish the Ring had never come to me.
我希望从没见过这枚魔戒
[ wish none of this had happened.
希望一切不曾发生
So do all who live to see such times. But that is not for them to decide.
经历困难的人都会这样想 但现实并不以他们的意志为转移
All we have to decide is what to do with the time that is given to us.
我们所能做的就是 在遇到困难时想办法去克服
There are other forces at work in this world, Frodo, besides the will of evil.
在这世上除了政恶的意志 还有其它力量的存在
Bilbo was meant to find the Ring.
比尔博命中注定会得到魔戒
In which case, you also were meant to have it.
从这个意义上讲 你得到它也是必然的
And that is an encouraging thought.
所以这个世界并不那么悲观
It's that way.
该走那边
-He's remembered. -No.
一他想起来了 -不
But the air doesn't smell so foul down here.
因为这里的空气不像刚才那样污浊
If in doubt, Meriadoc, always follow your nose.
当你拿不定主意的时候 孩子 那就跟着感觉走吧
Let me risk a little more light.
快给我点亮一支火炬
Behold...
快看
.. the great realm and Dwart-city of Dwarrowdelf.
壮丽的摩瑞亚王国和侏儒城
There's an eye opener, and no mistake.
真令人大开眼界
No!
不
"Here lies Balin...
摩瑞亚国王之子
..80n of Fundin...
巴林之墓
...Lord of Moria."
原来他已经不在了
He is dead, then.
正像我
It's as I feared.
我担心的那样
We must move on. We cannot linger.
我们必须前进 没时间犹豫
"They have taken the bridge and the second hall.
他们已经占领了大桥和二号大厅
We have barred the gates...
我们关闭了城门
...but cannot hold them for long.
但我们不会坚持很久
The ground shakes.
大地在颤拌
Drums...
战鼓
.. drums in the deep.
在记鸣
We cannot get out.
我们出不去了
A Shadow moves in the dark.
一个影子在黑暗中冲进来
They are coming."
他们来了
Fool of a Took!
你这个傻瓜
Throw yourself in next time, and rid us of your stupidity.
连你也跳进去 就不会给我们添廊烦了
Frodo!
佛罗多
Orcs.
半兽人
Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
快回来 不要离开甘道夫
They have a cave-troll.
他们有个山酒巨怪
Let them come!
让它们来吧
There is one Dwarf yet in Moria who still draws breath.
摩瑞亚侏癸还没有被斩尽杀绝
I think I'm getting the hang of this.
我想我找到穿门了
Frodo!
佛罗多
Aragorn! Aragorn!
阿拉贡 阿拉贡
Oh, no.
不
He's alive.
他还活着
I'm all right. I'm not hurt.
我没事 一点没受伤
You should be dead.
你怎么可能活着呢
That spear would have skewered a wild boar.
那长矛能杀头野猪
I think there's more to this Hobbit than meets the eye.
我想这位起比特人一定有什么绝招
Mithril.
银甲
You are full of surprises, Master Baggins.
你可真叫我们吃惊 巴金斯老爷
To the Bridge of Knazad-dim!
我们去找大桥
What is this new devilry?
又来了什么怪物?
A Balrog.
是炎魔怪
A demon of the ancient world.
一个远古的恶魔
This foe is beyond any of you.
我们绝不是它的对手
Run!
快跑吧
Gandalf.
甘道夫
Lead them on, Aragorn.
快继续往前跑
The bridge is near.
大桥就在附近
Do as I say! Swords are no more use here.
听我的 宝剑不能解决问题
Gandalfl
甘道夫
Merry! Pippin!
梅里 皮平
Sam!
山姆
Nobody tosses a Dwarf.
用不着 侏儒人用不着帮助
Not the beard!
我的明子
Steady.
等等
Hold on!
快
Hang on!
站稳
Lean forward!
探出身子
Steady.
稳住
Come on!
快点
Now!
跳
Over the bridge!
快上桥
Fly!
快点
You cannot pass!
你过不来
Gandalfl
甘道夫
lam a servant of the Secret Fire, wielder of the flame of Anor.
我是圣灵的仆人 上帝的守护者
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Uddin!
炎魔怪 你的那恶之火帮不了你
Go back to the Shadow.
滚回黑暗中去吧
You shall not pass!
你休想过来
-No! No! -Gandalfl
-不不 一鞭道夫
Fly, you fools!
快跑 傻瓜
No!
不
Aragorn!
阿拉贡
Legolas, get them up.
莱艾拉斯 让大家起来
Give them a moment, for pity's sake!
行行好 让他们静一会吧
By nightfall, these hills will be swarming with Orcs.
一旦天黑山上到处都是半兽人
We must reach the woods of Lothldrien.
我们必须要赶到罗斯洛立森林
Come, Boromir. Legolas. Gimli, get them up.
快博罗米尔 莱戈拉斯 金勇 起来
On your feet, Sam.
快起来 山姆
Frodo?
佛罗多
Stay close, young Hobbits!
大家靠近一些
They say that a great sorceress lives in these woods.
传说这片林子里有个高大的女巫
An Elf-witch...
一个强大无比的
...Of terrible power.
精灵巫师
All who look upon her...
任何抬头看她的人
.. fall under her spell.
都会被她迷倒
Frodo!
佛罗多
And are never seen again.
并会永远失明
Your coming to us is as the footsteps of doom.
你们的到来让我听到了死亡的脚步
You bring great evil here, Ring-bearer.
你帝来了万恶之源 至尊魔戒
Mr. Frodo?
佛罗多老他
Well, here's one Dwarf she won't ensnare so easily.
本侏儒可不是那么容易 让她给吓倒的
I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox.
我有鹰一样的眼睛和狐狸般的耳休
The Dwarf breathes so loud, we could have shot him in the dark.
这个矮子如此狂妄 刚才就该给他一箭
Aragorn, these woods are perilous. We should go back.
这里的丛林危机四伏 我们应该回去
You have entered the realm of the Lady of the Wood. You cannot go back.
你们进入了森林女王的领地 已经回不去了
Come. She is waiting.
走吧 她在等你们
Eight there are here, yet nine there were set out from Rivendell.
怎么只有8个 你们离开 瑞文戴尔时应该是9个
Tell me, where is Gandalf?
告诉我甘道夫去哪儿了
For l much desire to speak with him.
我非常想跟他谈谈
He has fallen into Shadow.
他已经落入深渊
The quest stands upon the edge of a knife.
你们的任务危险无比
Stray but a little and it will fail...
稍有不慎就将会
.. to the ruin of all.
全军覆灭
Yet hope remains while the Company is true.
但只要矢志不渝就不会失去希望
Do not let your hearts be troubled. Go now and rest...
但愿你们不要丧失信心 去休息吧
.. for you are weary with sorrow and much toil.
你们已经身心疲惫
Tonight, you will sleep....
今晚睡个好党
Welcome, Frodo of the Shire...
欢迎你 夏尔国的佛罗多
...one who has seen the Eye!
望着我的眼睛的人
A lament for Gandalf.
他们为甘道夫唱换歌
What do they say about him?
唱的什么?
I have not the heart to tell you. For me, the grief is still too near.
我实在不忍心告诉你 悲伤笼罩着我的心
Take some rest.
好好休息吧
These borders are well-protected.
我们在这儿很安全
[ will find no rest here.
可是我无法休息
I heard her voice inside my head.
我的脑海里回沪着她的歌声
She spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor.
她唱到我的父亲和刚铎的误落
She said to me, "Even now there is hope left."
她对我说直到今天还有和希望
But I cannot see it.
可我一点也看不到
It is long since we had any hope.
希望时就化成了泡影
My father is a noble man.
我父亲是个高尚的人
But his rule is failing...
可是他的统治土朋瓦解
..and our people lose faith.
人民失去了信心
He looks to me to make things right, and I would do it.
他和希望我能够重振国威 我会尽力的
I would see the glory of Gondor restored.
我要让刚铎重新辉煌
Have you ever seen it, Aragorn?
你见过吗 阿拉贡
The White Tower of Ecthelion.
爱克西里昂的白塔
Glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver.
银光闪闪 直刺蓝天
Its banners caught high in the morning breeze.
他的旗帜在晨风中猎猎球扬
Have you ever been called home...
你是否也曾
...by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
被军号召唤回家?
I have seen the White City...
折塔城我去过
.. long ago.
很久以前
One day, our paths will lead us there.
总有一天 我们会到达那里
And the tower guard shall take up the call:
自塔的卫士会再次宣布
"The Lords of Gondor have returned."
刚铎的国王回来了
Will you look into the mirror?
请你看看镜子好吗
What willl see?
我会看到什么?
Even the wisest cannot tell.
就连最聪明的人
For the mirror...
也无法预知
.. shows many things.
那里面有着太多的东西
Things that were...
过去的
... things that are...
现在的
..and some things...
还有一些
.. that have not yet come to pass.
未曾发生过的事情
I Know what it is you saw.
我知道你看见了什么
For it is also in my mind.
因为它在我的心里
It is what will come to pass if you should fail.
如果你们失败了 那些事情注定会发生
The Fellowship is breaking. It is already begun.
护戒使者会分裂 而且已经开始分裂
He will try to take the Ring.
那人试图夺取至尊魔戒
You know of whom ! speak.
你知道我说的是谁
One by one, it will destroy them all.
至苯魔戒会把他们一个个毁灭
If you ask it of me...
如果你向我索要
...f will give you the One Ring.
我会把至尊魔戒拱手相送
You Offer it to me freely.
你愿意把它交给我
I do not deny that my heart has greatly desired this.
不用说我心里对它渴望已久
In place of a Dark Lord, you would have a queen...
你们将会有一个女王取代黑暗魔君
..not dark but beautiful, and terrible as the dawn!
她虽然美丽但 好会像黎明一样恐怖
Treacherous as the sea!
像大海一样奸诠
Stronger than the foundations of the earth!
像造物主一样强大
All shall love me...
所有的人都会
..and despair.
绝望地爱着我
I pass the test. I will diminish...
我经受住了考验 我的力量会减弱
..and go into the West...
我要去西方
-...and remain Galadriel. -I cannot do this alone.
=我还是盖拉德丽尔 -我自己无法毁掉它
You are a Ring-bearer, Frodo. To bear a Ring of Power...
你是魔戒的持有者 佛罗多 拥有魔戒的魔力
.. I$ to be alone.
你注定是要孤单的
This task was appointed to you.
这是你的使命
And if you do not find a way...
如果你做不到
...No one will.
那就没人能行
Then I know what I must do.
我知道我该做什么了
It's just...
可我还是
.. I'm afraid to do it.
还是有些担心
Even the smallest person can change the course of the future.
就连最不起眼的人也能改变历史
Hunt them down. Do not stop until they are found.
找到他们 否则别回来见我
You do not Know pain. You do not Know fear.
你们不知道疼痛不知道恐惧
You will taste Man-flesh!
你们会品尝到人的滋味
One of the halflings carries something of great value.
有个矮人带着一件价值连城的珠宝 你们要带他来见我
Kill the others.
其他人 格杀勿论
Farewell, Frodo Baggins.
再见 佛罗多“' 巴金斯
I give you the light of Earendil...
我把埃兰迪尔之光送给你
...our most beloved star.
我们最珍贵的明星
May it be a light for you in dark places...
愿黑暗笼田一切的时候
... when all other lights go out.
它会为你带来光明
Frodo.
佛罗多 看
The Argonath.
亚格那斯
Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old.
我一直希望日睹父辈的风采
My kin.
我的祖先
We cross the lake at nightfall.
我们要趁着夜色划到湖对岸去
Hide the boats and continue on foot.
把船藏好之后继续步行
-We approach Mordor from the North. -Oh, yes?
-然后从北面接近魔多 一是吗
Just a simple matter of finding our way through Emyn Mull...
穿越爱明莫尔山实在太容易了
..an impassable labyrinth of razor-sharp rocks.
因为它那峰利无比的 岩石迷宫根本无法通行
And after that, it gets even better.
更有意思的还在后面
Festering, stinking marshland as far as the eye can see.
那就是一望无际奇臭无比的沼泽地
That is our road.
我们别无选择
I suggest you take some rest and recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
好好休息 养精蓄锐吧 侏儒老分
Recover my--
鬼才要休息
-We should leave now. -No.
- 应该马上出发 -不
Orcs patrol the eastern shore. We must wait for cover of darkness.
半兽人守住东岸 我们必须借助夜幕的掩护
It is not the eastern shore that worries me.
让人担心的并不是东岸
A shadow and a threat has been growing in my mind.
我的心头有种不祥的预感
Something draws near. I can feel it.
好像要发生什么事情 我能感觉到
Recover strength? Pay no heed to that, young Hobbit.
侏儒从不需要休息 别听他的 震比特小伙
Where's Frodo?
佛罗多呢?
None of us should wander alone.
我们不应该单独行动
You, least of all.
尤其是你
So much depends on you.
你的责任重大
Frodo?
佛罗多
I Know why you seek solitude.
我知道你为什么喜欢一个人独处
You suffer. I see it day by day.
你很痛苦 我都看在眼里
You sure you do not suffer needlessly?
你不认为你的痛苦很无谓吗
There are other ways, Frodo.
我们还有其它的路可走
-Other paths that we might take. -I know what you would say.
一并不是山穷水尽 一我知道你想说什么
It would seem like wisdom but for the warning in my heart.
尽管那样做很明智 但我的心在罗告我
Warning? Against what?
警告? 警告什么
We're all afraid, Frodo.
我们都很害怕 佛罗多
But to let that fear drive us, to destroy what hope we have...
但如果让恐惧左右我们 使我们放弃希望
-...don't you see that is madness? -There is no other way.
=- 你不觉得那很疯狂吗 一我们别无选择
l ask only for the strength to defend my people!
我只求我的力量保护我的人民
-If you would but lend me the Ring. -No.
-如果你把魔戒借我一用 - 不行
-Why do you recoil? ! am no thief. -You are not yourself.
-你怕什么 我又不是穷贼 -可你已经不是你自己了
What chance do you think you have?
你认为有多大的胜算
They will find you. They will take the Ring.
他们会找到你 他们会夺走魔戒
And you will beg for death before the end!
到那时候你会走投无路的
You fool!
傻瓜 它不属于你
It should be mine! Give it to me!
它应该是我的 把它给我
-Give it to me! -No!
- 快给我 -不
-No.
- 给我
I see your mind.
我知道你在想什么
You will take the Ring to Sauron!
你想把魔戒交给索伦
You will betray us!
你想出卖我们
You'll go to your death, and the death of us all!
你自己找死还要连累我们大家
Curse you! Curse you and all the halflings!
我诅台你 诅咒你和所有的矮人
Frodo?
佛罗多
What have I done?
我做了什么?
Please, Frodo.
求求你 佛罗多
Frodo, I'm sorry!
对不起 佛罗多
Frodo?
佛罗多
-It has taken Boromir. -Where is the Ring?
一它已经患惑了博罗米尔 -那至尊魔戒在哪儿
Stay away!
你走开
Frodo!
佛罗多
-I swore to protect you. -Can you protect me from yourself?
-我发拆会保护你的 -你能保护你自己吗
Would you destroy it?
你能毁掉它吗
Aragorn.
阿拉贡
Elessar.
伊力萨
I would have gone with you to the end.
我会一直陪伴你的
Into the very fires of Mordor.
一直陪你到魔多火山
I know.
我知道
Look after the others. Especially Sam. He will not understand.
你照顾好其他人 尤其是山姆 他比较迟钝
Go, Frodo!
快跑 佛罗多
Run.
快
Mr. Frodo!
佛罗多老他
Find the halfling!
找到矮人
Elendil!
埃兰迪尔
Aragorn, go!
阿拉贡 快走
Frodo!
佛罗多
Hide here. Quick!
藏这儿
Come on!
快过来
What's he doing?
他在干什么
He's leaving.
他要自己走
-No! -Pippin!
-不 -皮平
Run, Frodo. Go on!
快跑 佛罗多
-Hey! Hey, you! -Over here!
-了虽说你呢 - 快过来
-This way!
一这里
-It's working! -l know it's working! Run!
有戏了 =-我知道 快跑
-The horn of Gondor. -Boromir.
-是刚色的号角 -是博罗米尔
Run!
快跑 快
No.
不
-They took the little ones. -Hold still.
一他们抓走了矮人 一别说话
Frodo. Where is Frodo?
佛罗多在哪儿?
I let Frodo go.
我让他走了
Then you did what I could not.
你做了我没能做的事
I tried to take the Ring from him.
我本来想拿到他的魔戒
-The Ring is beyond our reach now. -Forgive me.
=-我们现在谁都拿不到了 - 原谅我
I did not see it.
我受了趾惑
-l have failed you all. -No, Boromir.
=-我春负了你们大家 -不博罗米尔
You fought bravely.
你作战很勇敢
You have kept your honor.
你维护了自己的荣誉
Leave it.
别拔了
It is over.
都过去了
I do not know what strength is in my blood...
我不知道自己的血还有多热
...but swear to you, [ will not let the White City fall...
但是我保证不会让晴朗的世界消失
...nor our people fail.
不会让人民震难
Our people.
我们的人民
I would have followed you, my brother.
我将和你一起战斗 我的兄弟
My captain.
我的首领
My king.
我的国王
Be at peace...
安息吧
...8on of Gondor.
刚铎的儿子
Frodo!
佛罗多
! wish the Ring had never come to me.
我希望从没见过这枚魔戒
! wish none of this had happened.
希望这一切从未发生
So do all who live to see such times...
经历过困难的人都会这样想
...but that is not for them to decide.
但现实并不以他们的意志为转移
All you have to decide...
我们所能做的
...is what to do with the time that is given to you.
就是在遇到困难时想办法去克服
Frodo, no!
佛罗多 别这样
Frodo!
佛罗多
-Mr. Frodo! -No, Sam.
一佛罗多老爷 -不山姆
Go back, Sam!
快回去 山姆
-I'm going to Mordor alone. -Of course you are.
-我要一个人去魔多 一你当然自己去
And I'm coming with you!
我不能陪你
You can't swim!
你不会游泳
Sam!
山姆
I made a promise, Mr. Frodo.
我起过故 佛罗多老他
A promise: "Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."
我对自己说 不要离开他 山姆怀斯 甘姆齐
And don't mean to.
我不能离开你
I don't mean to.
别丢下我
Sam.
山姆
Come on.
我们走吧
Hurry! Frodo and Sam have reached the eastern shore.
快 佛罗多和山姆 也许已经达到东兰
-You mean not to follow them. -Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
-你是说不要去追他们 -佛罗多的命运与我们无关了
Then it has all been in vain. The Fellowship has failed.
这么说我们直忙一场 护戒使者功亏一黄
Not if we hold true to each other.
只要我们彼此忠诚就不算是白忙
We will not abandon Merry and Pippin to torment and death.
只要还有一口气就不能让 梅里和皮平痛苦地死去
Not while we have strength left. Leave all that can be spared behind.
扔掉一切可以扔掉的东西 向着光明前进吧
We travel light.
来吧 伙计们
Let us hunt some Orc.
找半兽人算账去
Yes!
好吧
I hope the others find a safer road.
我希望他们找到更安全的路
Strider will look after them.
健步侠会照顾他们
I don't suppose we'll ever see them again.
丽怕我们再也见不到他们了
We may yet, Mr. Frodo.
会见到的 佛罗多
We may.
会的
Sam...
山姆
...l'm glad you are with me.
真高兴能和你在一起